So a couple of years ago I started a program
حسنا، بدأت برنامجا قبل سنوات خلت
to try to get the rockstar tech and design people
لمحاولة جعل تقنيي نجوم الروك والمهتمين بالتصميم
to take a year off
للتفرغ لسنة
and work in the one environment
والعمل في محيط واحد
that represents pretty much everything they're supposed to hate;
يمثل إلى حد كبير كل شيء يفترض بهم كرهه؛
we have them work in government.
جعلناهم يشتغلون في الحكومة.
The program is called Code for America,
البرنامج يدعى البرمجة لأجل أمريكا،
and it's a little bit like a Peace Corps for geeks.
وهو أمر يشبه نوعا ما فيلق السلام لمهووسي التكنولوجيا.
We select a few fellows every year
نختار بضعة زملاء كل سنة
and we have them work with city governments.
ونجعلهم يشتغلون في الحكومات المدنية.
Instead of sending them off into the Third World,
بدل إرسالهم إلى العالم الثالث،
we send them into the wilds of City Hall.
نرسلهم إلى أدغال قاعة البلدية.
And there they make great apps, they work with city staffers.
وهنالك يصممون تطبيقات مذهلة، يشتغلون مع موظفي المدينة.
But really what they're doing is they're showing what's possible
لكن في الواقع ما يقومون به هو أنهم يظهرون ما هو ممكن
with technology today.
من التكنولوجيا اليوم.
So meet Al.
حسنا قابلوا آل.
Al is a fire hydrant in the city of Boston.
آل هو صنبور إطفاء في مدينة بوسطن.
Here it kind of looks like he's looking for a date,
يبدو هنا وكأنه يبحث عن موعد غرامي،
but what he's really looking for is for someone to shovel him out when he gets snowed in,
لكن ما يبحث حقا عنه هو أن يزيح عنه أحدهم الثلج حين يغطيه،
because he knows he's not very good at fighting fires
لأنه يعرف أنه ليس جيدا جدا في محاربة الحرائق
when he's covered in four feet of snow.
حين يكون مغطى بأربع أقدام من الثلج.
Now how did he come to be looking for help
الآن كيف استطاع أن يبحث عن المساعدة
in this very unique manner?
بهذه الطريقة الفريدة؟
We had a team of fellows in Boston last year
كان لدينا فريق من الزملاء في بوسطن السنة الماضية
through the Code for America program.
عن طريق برنامج: البرمجة لأجل أمريكا.
They were there in February, and it snowed a lot in February last year.
كانوا هناك في فبراير، وقد أثلجت كثيرا في فبراير السنة الماضية.
And they noticed that the city never gets
وقد لاحظوا أن المدينة لا تقوم أبدا
to digging out these fire hydrants.
بحفر صنابير الإطفاء تلك.
But one fellow in particular,
لكن زميلا واحدا على وجه الخصوص،
a guy named Erik Michaels-Ober,
شخص يدعى إريك مايكلز-أوبير،
noticed something else,
لاحظ أمرا آخر،
and that's that citizens are shoveling out sidewalks
وذلك أن المواطنين يجرفون الممرات
right in front of these things.
تماما أمام تلك الأشياء.
So he did what any good developer would do,
وبالتالي قام بما قد يقوم به أي مطور جيد،
he wrote an app.
برمج تطبيقا.
It's a cute little app where you can adopt a fire hydrant.
إنه تطبيق صغير وجذاب حيث يمكنك أن تتبنى صنبور إطفاء.
So you agree to dig it out when it snows.
وبالتالي توافق على حفره حين تثلج.
If you do, you get to name it,
إن قمت بذلك، تتاح لك تسميته،
and he called the first one Al.
وقد أطلق على الأول اسم آل.
And if you don't, someone can steal it from you.
وإن لم تفعلوا، شخص آخر يمكن أن يسرقه منكم.
So it's got cute little game dynamics on it.
وبالتالي فإنه يحوي لعبة صغيرة جذابة فيه.
This is a modest little app.
هذا تطبيق صغير متواضع.
It's probably the smallest
إنه على الأرجح أصغر
of the 21 apps that the fellows wrote last year.
21 تطبيقا برمجها هذا الزميل في السنة الماضية.
But it's doing something
لكنه يؤدي وظيفة
that no other government technology does.
لا تستطيع أي تكنولوجيا حكومية تأديتها.
It's spreading virally.
إنه ينتشر بشكل فيروسي.
There's a guy in the I.T. department of the City of Honolulu
هناك شخص في قسم تكنولوجيا المعلومات لمدينة هونولولو
who saw this app and realized
رآى هذا التطبيق وتيقن
that he could use it, not for snow,
أنه يمكن أن يستخدمه، ليس للثلج،
but to get citizens to adopt tsunami sirens.
لكن لجعل المواطنين يتبنون صافرات التسونامي.
It's very important that these tsunami sirens work,
من المهم أن تشتغل صافرات التسونامي هذه
but people steal the batteries out of them.
لكن الناس يسرقون منها البطاريات.
So he's getting citizens to check on them.
لذا فهو يجعل المواطنين يتحققون منها.
And then Seattle decided to use it
ومن ثم قررت سياتل استخدامه
to get citizens to clear out clogged storm drains.
لجعل المواطنين ينظفون مصارف مياه العواصف المسدودة.
And Chicago just rolled it out
وشيكاغو استخدمته
to get people to sign up to shovel sidewalks when it snows.
لجعل الناس للتسجيل لتنظيف الممرات حين تثلج.
So we now know of nine cities
لذا فنحن الآن نعرف بخصوص تسع مدن
that are planning to use this.
تخطط لاستخدام هذا.
And this has spread just frictionlessly,
وهذا قد انتشر بدون احتكاك،
organically, naturally.
بعضوية، وبطبيعية.
If you know anything about government technology,
إن كنتم تعرفون أي شيء بخصوص التكنولوجيا الحكومية،
you know that this isn't how it normally goes.
تعرفون أن الأمور لا تسير هكذا عادة.
Procuring software usually takes a couple of years.
شراء البرمجيات يستغرق عادة بضع سنوات.
We had a team that worked on a project in Boston last year
كان لدينا فريق يعمل على مشروع في السنة الماضية
that took three people about two and a half months.
استغرق ثلاث أشخاص حوالي الشهرين والنصف.
It was a way that parents could figure out
لقد كانت طريقة يستطيع من خلاله الآباء معرفة
which were the right public schools for their kids.
ما هي المدارس العمومية الأحسن لأطفالهم.
We were told afterward that if that had gone through normal channels,
تم إخبارنا لاحقا أنه إن تم تمرير ذلك في القنوات الرسمية،
it would have taken at least two years
قد يستغرق عامين على الأقل
and it would have cost about two million dollars.
وسيكلف حوالي مليوني دولار.
And that's nothing.
وهذا لا شيء.
There is one project in the California court system right now
هناك مشروع في نظام محاكم كاليفورنيا الآن
that so far cost taxpayers
يكلف دافعي الضرائب لحد الآن
two billion dollars,
ملياري دولار،
and it doesn't work.
وهو لا يشتغل.
And there are projects like this
وهناك مشاريع كهذه
at every level of government.
في كل مستوى من الحكومة.
So an app that takes a couple of days to write
حسنا التطبيق الذي يستغرق بضعة أيام لبرمجته
and then spreads virally,
ومن ثم ينتشر بشكل فيروسي،
that's sort of a shot across the bow
ذلك نوع من الطلقة المنحنية
to the institution of government.
لمؤسسات الحكومة.
It suggests how government could work better --
إنه يقترح الطريقة التي قد تعمل بها الحكومة بشكل أفضل --
not more like a private company,
ليس أكثر مثل شركات خاصة،
as many people think it should.
كما يظن بعض الناس أنه يجدر بها القيام بذات الامر .
And not even like a tech company,
وليس حتى مثل شركة تكنولوجية،
but more like the Internet itself.
لكن أكثر مثل الأنترنيت نفسه.
And that means permissionless,
وهذا يعني بدون ترخيص،
it means open, it means generative.
هذا يعني مصادر مفتوحة، هذا يعني توليدية.
And that's important.
وذلك مهم.
But what's more important about this app
لكن الأكثر أهمية بخصوص هذا التطبيق
is that it represents how a new generation
هو أنه يمثل كيف يمكن لجيل جديد
is tackling the problem of government --
أن يعالج مشاكل الحكومة --
not as the problem of an ossified institution,
ليس كمشكلة مؤسسة متحجرة،
but as a problem of collective action.
لكن كمشكلة للعمل الجماعي.
And that's great news,
وتلك أخبار جيدة،
because, it turns out, we're very good at collective action
لأنه يبدو أننا جيدون جدا في الأعمال الجماعية
with digital technology.
بالتكنولوجيا الرقمية.
Now there's a very large community of people
الآن هناك مجموعة من الناس
that are building the tools that we need
يبنون أداة نحتاجها
to do things together effectively.
للقيام بالأمور معا بشكل أكثر فاعلية.
It's not just Code for America fellows,
ليس فقط زملاء "البرمجة لأجل أمريكا"،
there are hundreds of people all over the country
هناك مئات الأشخاص في جميع أرجاء الدولة
that are standing and writing civic apps
يقفون ويبرمجون تطبيقات مدنية
every day in their own communities.
في كل يوم في مجتمعاتهم.
They haven't given up on government.
لم ييأسوا من الحكومة بعد.
They are frustrated as hell with it,
هم محبطون للغاية منها
but they're not complaining about it,
لكنهم لا يشتكون من ذلك،
they're fixing it.
إنهم يصلحونه.
And these folks know something
وهؤلاء الأشخاص يعرفون شيئا
that we've lost sight of.
غاب عن بالنا.
And that's that when you strip away all your feelings
وهو أنه حين تتجرد من كل مشاعرك
about politics and the line at the DMV
حول السياسة والصف في إدارة المركبات الآلية
and all those other things
وكل تلك الأمور الأخرى
that we're really mad about,
التي نحن غاضبون للغاية بخصوصها،
government is, at its core,
الحكومة هي، في جوهرها،
in the words of Tim O'Reilly,
بكلمات تيم أوريلي،
"What we do together that we can't do alone."
"ما نقوم به معا ولا يمكن أن نقوم به منفردين."
Now a lot of people have given up on government.
الآن الكثير من الناس قد يئسوا من الحكومة.
And if you're one of those people,
وإن كنت أحد هؤلاء الناس،
I would ask that you reconsider,
أسألكم أن تعيدوا النظر،
because things are changing.
لأن الأمور تتغير.
Politics is not changing;
السياسات لا تتغير؛
government is changing.
الحكومات تتغير.
And because government
ولأن الحكومة
ultimately derives its power from us --
تستمد قوتها في النهاية منا --
remember "We the people?" --
تذكروا "نحن الناس؟"--
how we think about it
كيف نفكر حيال ذلك
is going to effect how that change happens.
سيؤثر على كيفية حدوث التغيير.
Now I didn't know very much about government when I started this program.
الآن لم أعرف الكثير حول الحكومة حين بدأت هذا البرنامج.
And like a lot of people,
ومثل الكثير من الناس،
I thought government was basically about getting people elected to office.
كنت أظن أن الحكومة كانت في الأساس حول انتخاب الناس للمناصب.
Well after two years, I've come to the conclusion
حسنا بعد سنتين، وصلت إلى خلاصة
that, especially local government,
أنه، وبالخصوص الحكومات المحلية،
is about opossums.
تتعلق بالأبوبوسومات.
This is the call center for the services and information line.
هذا مركز الإتصال لخط الخدمات والمعلومات.
It's generally where you will get
إنه على العموم حيث تصل
if you call 311 in your city.
حين تتصل ب311 في مدينتك.
If you should ever have the chance
إن كانت لديك قط الفرصة لذلك
to staff your city's call center,
هو توظيف الناس في مراكز الإتصال،
as our fellow Scott Silverman did as part of the program --
كما فعل سكوت سيلفرمات كجزء من البرنامج --
in fact, they all do that --
في الواقع، جميعهم يقومون بذلك --
you will find that people call government
ستجد أن الناس يتصلون بالحكومة
with a very wide range of issues,
بمجموعة واسعة جدا من القضايا،
including having an opossum stuck in your house.
تشمل أوبوسوما منحشرا في بيتكم.
So Scott gets this call.
إذن فسكوت تصله هذه المكالمة.
He types "Opossum" into this official knowledge base.
يكتب "أوبوسوم" في قاعدة المعرفة الرسمية.
He doesn't really come up with anything. He starts with animal control.
لا يأتي بأي جديد. فقط يبدأ مع التحكم في الحيوانات.
And finally, he says, "Look, can you just open all the doors to your house
وفي النهاية، يقول، "انظر، هل في إمكانك أن تفتح كل أبواب منزلك
and play music really loud
وشغل الموسيقى بشكل صاخب جدا
and see if the thing leaves?"
وانظر إن كان ذلك الشيء قد غادر؟"
So that worked. So booya for Scott.
حسنا فذلك قد نجح. مرحى لسكوت.
But that wasn't the end of the opossums.
لكن تلك لم تكن نهاية الأوبوسوم.
Boston doesn't just have a call center.
بوسطن لا تتوفر فقط على مركز اتصالات.
It has an app, a Web and mobile app,
لديها تطبيق، تطبيق ويب وأجهزة محمولة،
called Citizens Connect.
يدعى "اتصال المواطنين".
Now we didn't write this app.
الآن نحن لم نبرمج هذا التطبيق.
This is the work of the very smart people
هذا عمل أشخاص الأذكياء جدا
at the Office of New Urban Mechanics in Boston.
في مكتب نيو أوربان ميكانيكس في بوسطن.
So one day -- this is an actual report -- this came in:
حسنا في أحد الأيام -- وهذا تقرير حقيقي -- ورد هذا:
"Opossum in my trashcan. Can't tell if it's dead.
"هناك أوبوسوم في مكب نفاياتي. لا أستطيع الجزم إن كان ميتا.
How do I get this removed?"
كيف أزيل هذا؟"
But what happens with Citizens Connect is different.
لكن ما حدث مع "اتصال المواطنين" مختلف.
So Scott was speaking person-to-person.
فسكوت كان يتحدث وجها لوجه.
But on Citizens Connect everything is public,
لكن في "اتصال المواطنين" كل شيء عام،
so everybody can see this.
وبالتالي يستطيع الجميع رؤية هذا.
And in this case, a neighbor saw it.
وفي هذه الحالة، رآه أحد الجيران.
And the next report we got said,
والتقرير التالي الذي تلقيناه يقول،
"I walked over to this location,
"ذهبت إلى المكان،
found the trashcan behind the house.
وجدت مكب النفايات خلف المنزل.
Opossum? Check. Living? Yep.
أوبوسوم؟ تم التحقق. حي؟ نعم.
Turned trashcan on its side. Walked home.
قلبت صندوق القمامة جانبا. ومشيت نحو بيتي.
Goodnight sweet opossum."
ليلة سعيدة أيها الأوبوسوم الحلو."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Pretty simple.
في غاية البساطة.
So this is great. This is the digital meeting the physical.
إذن فهذا عظيم. هنا يلتقي ما هو رقمي بما هو مادي.
And it's also a great example
وهو كذلك مثال عظيم
of government getting in on the crowd-sourcing game.
عن دخول الحكومة إلى لعبة التعهيد الجماعي.
But it's also a great example of government as a platform.
لكنه كذلك مثال عظيم للحكومة كمنصة.
And I don't mean necessarily
ولا أعني بالضرورة
a technological definition of platform here.
التعريف التقني للمنصة هنا.
I'm just talking about a platform for people
أنا فقط أتحدث عن منصة للناس
to help themselves and to help others.
ليساعدوا أنفسهم وغيرهم.
So one citizen helped another citizen,
إذن فمواطن ساعد مواطنا آخر،
but government played a key role here.
لكن الحكومة لعبت دورا محوريا هنا.
It connected those two people.
قامت بربط هذين الشخصين.
And it could have connected them with government services if they'd been needed,
وقد كانت لتربطهم بالخدمات الحكومية إن كانوا في حاجة لها،
but a neighbor is a far better and cheaper alternative
لكن الجار بديل أحسن وأرخص بكثير
to government services.
للخدمات الحكومية.
When one neighbor helps another,
حين يساعد جار آخر،
we strengthen our communities.
نقوي مجتمعاتنا.
We call animal control, it just costs a lot of money.
إن اتصلنا بخدمة "مراقبة الحيوانات"، فذلك يكلف الكثير من المال.
Now one of the important things we need to think about government
الآن أحد أهم الأمور التي نحتاج للتفكير فيها بخصوص الحكومة
is that it's not the same thing as politics.
هو أنها ليست مثل السياسة.
And most people get that,
ومعظم الناس يعون ذلك،
but they think that one is the input to the other.
لكنهم يظنون أن إحداهما مدخلة الأخرى.
That our input to the system of government
أن مدخلنا لنظام الحكومة
is voting.
هو التصويت.
Now how many times have we elected a political leader --
الآن كم من مرة انتخبنا قائدا سياسيا--
and sometimes we spend a lot of energy
وأحيانا نستهلك طاقة كبيرة
getting a new political leader elected --
في انتخاب قائد سياسي جديد --
and then we sit back and we expect government
فنجلس ونتوقع من الحكومة
to reflect our values and meet our needs,
أن تعكس قيمنا وتلبي حاجياتنا،
and then not that much changes?
وبالتالي لا يتغير الكثير؟
That's because government is like a vast ocean
هذا لأن الحكومة هي مثل محيط كبير
and politics is the six-inch layer on top.
والسياسة هي طبقة الست إنشات فوقها.
And what's under that
وما تحت ذلك
is what we call bureaucracy.
هو ما نسميه البيروقراطية.
And we say that word with such contempt.
ونتلفظ بتلك الكلمة بنوع من الازدراء.
But it's that contempt
لكن ذلك الازدراء
that keeps this thing that we own
هو ما يجعل هذا الشيء الذي نملكه
and we pay for
ونؤدي عنه
as something that's working against us, this other thing,
يشتغل ضدنا، هذا الشيء الآخر،
and then we're disempowering ourselves.
وهكذا فنحن نجرد أنفسنا من القوة.
People seem to think politics is sexy.
يبدو أن الناس يعتقدون أن السياسة جذابة.
If we want this institution to work for us,
إن أردنا لهذه المؤسسة أن تعمل لأجلنا،
we're going to have to make bureaucracy sexy.
علينا أن نعمل لجعل البيروقراطية جذابة.
Because that's where the real work of government happens.
لأن ذلك حيث يحدث العمل الحكومي الحقيقي.
We have to engage with the machinery of government.
علينا أن نتشارك مع أجهزة الحكومة.
So that's OccupytheSEC movement has done.
لذا فهذا ما فعلته حركة OccupytheSEC .
Have you seen these guys?
هل رأيتم هؤلاء الأشخاص؟
It's a group of concerned citizens
إنهم مجموعة من المواطنين المهتمين
that have written a very detailed
كتبوا بتفصيل
325-page report
تقريرا من 325 صفحة
that's a response to the SEC's request for comment
كإجابة على طلب SEC للتعليق
on the Financial Reform Bill.
على مسودة قانون الإصلاح المالي.
That's not being politically active,
هذا لا يعد كون المرء فاعلا سياسيا،
that's being bureaucratically active.
بل كونه فاعلا بيروقراطيا.
Now for those of us who've given up on government,
الآن بالنسبة للذين قد يئسوا من الحكومة منا،
it's time that we asked ourselves
حان الوقت لنسأل أنفسنا
about the world that we want to leave for our children.
حول العالم الذي نريد أن نتركه لأطفالنا.
You have to see the enormous challenges
عليكم أن تروا التحديات الهائلة
that they're going to face.
التي سيواجهونها.
Do we really think we're going to get where we need to go
هل نعتقد فعلا أننا سنصل حيث نريد
without fixing the one institution
بدون إصلاح المؤسسة الوحيد
that can act on behalf of all of us?
التي تعمل نيابة عنا؟
We can't do without government,
لا نستطيع العمل بدون الحكومة،
but we do need it
لكننا نحتاجها
to be more effective.
أن تكون أكثر فاعلية.
The good news is that technology is making it possible
الأخبار الجيدة هو أن التكنولوجيا تتيح
to fundamentally reframe
إعادة صياغة جذرية
the function of government
لوظيفة الحكومة
in a way that can actually scale
بطريقة يمكنها بالفعل التدرج
by strengthening civil society.
في تعزيز المجتمع المدني.
And there's a generation out there that's grown up on the Internet,
وهناك جيل نشأ على الأنترنيت،
and they know that it's not that hard
وهم يعلمون أنها ليس من الصعب
to do things together,
القيام بالأمور معا،
you just have to architect the systems the right way.
عليك فقط هندسة الأنظمة بالطريقة الصحيحة.
Now the average age of our fellows is 28,
الآن العمر المتوسط لزملائنا هو 28،
so I am, begrudgingly,
وكذلك أنا، بحسد،
almost a generation older than most of them.
أكبر منهم بجيل كامل تقريبا.
This is a generation
هذا جيل
that's grown up taking their voices pretty much for granted.
نشأ باعتبار صوته من المسلمات.
They're not fighting that battle that we're all fighting
هم لا يخوضون المعركة التي نخوضها كلنا
about who gets to speak;
حول من يمكنه الحديث؛
they all get to speak.
كلهم يتاح لهم الحديث.
They can express their opinion
يمكنهم التعبير عن رأيهم
on any channel at any time,
على أي قناة في أي وقت،
and they do.
وهم يقومون بذلك.
So when they're faced with the problem of government,
وبالتالي حين يواجهون مشاكل الحكومة
they don't care as much
لا يهتمون كثيرا
about using their voices.
حول استخدام أصواتهم.
They're using their hands.
هم يستخدمون أيديهم.
They're using their hands
هم يستخدمون أيديهم
to write applications that make government work better.
لبرمجة تطبيقات تجعل الحكومة تشتغل بشكل أفضل.
And those applications let us use our hands
وتلك التطبيقات تسمح لنا باستخدام أيدينا
to make our communities better.
لجعل مجتمعاتنا أفضل.
That could be shoveling out a hydrant, pulling a weed,
قد يكون ذلك جرف الثلج عن صنبور المطافئ، سحب الأعشاب،
turning over a garbage can with an opossum in it.
قلب صندوق نفايات بداخله أوبوسوم.
And certainly, we could have been shoveling out those fire hydrants all along,
وبالتأكيد، يمكن أن نكون دائما نزيح الثلج عن صنابير المطافئ تلك،
and many people do.
والكثير من الناس يقومون بذلك.
But these apps are like little digital reminders
لكن هذه التطبيقات هي مثل منبهات رقمية
that we're not just consumers,
أننا لسنا فقط مستهلكين،
and we're not just consumers of government,
ولسنا فقط مستهلكين للحكومة،
putting in our taxes and getting back services.
ندفع ضرائبنا ونستفيد من الخدمات.
We're more than that,
نحن أكثر من ذلك،
we're citizens.
نحن مواطنون.
And we're not going to fix government
ولن نصلح الحكومة
until we fix citizenship.
إلا حين نصلح المواطنة.
So the question I have for all of you here:
لذا فالسؤال الذي لدي لجميعكم هنا:
When it comes to the big, important things
حين يتعلق الأمر بالأمور الكبيرة المهمة
that we need to do together,
والتي نحتاج للقيام بها معا،
all of us together,
كلنا جميعا
are we just going to be a crowd of voices,
هل سنكون فقط حشدا من الأصوات،
or are we also going to be
أم سنكون
a crowd of hands?
حشدا من الأيادي الفاعلة ؟
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)